<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great Turkes defiance: Or his letter denuntiatorie to Sigismond the Third, now King of Polonia as it hath beene truly aduertised out of Germany, this present yeere, 1613. With the King of Poland his replie, Englished according to the French copie, by M.S.</title>
            <author>Ahmed, I, Sultan of Turkey, 1590-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10314</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 206</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S122421</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857570</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857570</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23330</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10314)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23330)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 818:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great Turkes defiance: Or his letter denuntiatorie to Sigismond the Third, now King of Polonia as it hath beene truly aduertised out of Germany, this present yeere, 1613. With the King of Poland his replie, Englished according to the French copie, by M.S.</title>
                  <author>Ahmed, I, Sultan of Turkey, 1590-1617.</author>
                  <author>Sigismund III, King of Poland and Sweden, 1566-1632.</author>
                  <author>M. S., fl. 1613.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Melchisedech Bradwood, for William Aspley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The great Turke = Ahmed I.</note>
                  <note>French original not traced.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Poland --  Foreign relations --  Turkey --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Turkey --  Foreign relations --  Poland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:23330:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23330:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GREAT TVRKES DEFIANCE:</p>
            <p>Or his Letter DENVNTIATORIE to SIGISMOND the Third, now King of Polonia, as it hath beene truly aduertiſed out of Germany, this preſent yeere, 1613.</p>
            <p>WITH THE KING OF POLAND his replie, Engliſhed according to <hi>the French Copie,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By M. S.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>M B</head>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Melchiſedech Bradwood,</hi> for <hi>William Aſpley.</hi> 1613.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:23330:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23330:2"/>
            <head>THE COPPIE OF A DENVNCIATION ſent by the great Emperour <hi>of the Turkes,</hi> Vnto Sigiſmond the third, King of Poland <hi>and Lituania, the ſeuenth of Iulie,</hi> 1612.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>CMETH SOLDAN, Sonne of the moſt puiſſant and higheſt, Emperour of the Turks, King of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonia, Arabia, Samaria, Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, and little Egypt, King aboue
<pb facs="tcp:23330:3"/>
all the Kings that dwell vpon the earth, a King that dwelleth on the earthlie Paradice, an annointed Prince &amp; ſonne of Mahomet, Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lower Hungarie, Prior of the Earthly Paradice, and Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Graue of thy God, Lord of the tree of life, and of the Riuer Flisky, Conqueror of the Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, borders of Hungaria, and of the citie Bettune, a great perſecutor of his enemies, and of all their euill vices, a moſt perfect Iewell of the bleſſed Tree, the chiefeſt keeper of the crucified God, a Prince &amp; Lord in whom the Pagans truſt, and a great perſecutor of all Chriſtians.</signed>
               <salute>To <hi>SIGISMOND</hi> the Third, King of Poland our greeting,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>if thou doeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire our welfare, and art friend to vs and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:23330:3"/>
our Officer and Lieutenant Generall of our forces which we will ſend. But thou haſt long ſince broken and falſified our friendſhip, and yet art neither readie nor fit to wage warre or fight battell against vs. But thou haſt ſome ſecret aduiſe and intelligence with other confederate Kings, and their Counſellors, to deliuer thee out of our hands and our vicegerents power, wherein thou haſt done very vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduiſedly and vndiſcreetly. If therefore thou thus perſeuere to oppoſe thy ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, then feare, for thy death and the death of all thy people is determined. We tell thee we will ouercome thee from the riſing of the Sunne, to the going down thereof, and wee will ſhew our Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie in our owne perſon and ſight vnto the vttermoſt parts of the earth. Our verie thoughts ſhalbe a terror vnto thee, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:23330:4"/>
we will performe all that which we haue heerein denounced. And we will make knowne vnto thee the powerfulneſſe of our dominions. And thou, o King, which putteſt thy truſt in ſtrong forts &amp; Caſtles ſhalt haue experience of my might and power. I will root out all together, and thou ſhalt behold this with thine owne eies. Wherefore expect now no more friendſhip at my hands; put not thy hope in the ſtrength of thy walles, with thy owne forces and people. J will ruinate thee without any reſiſtance. J will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy thy Craccawe in ſigne of triumph. J will leaue there my bloody ſword, that euerie one ſhall take notice thereof, and my beleefe ſhalbe ſpread abroad thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all thy Dominions, and I will vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly root out the very remembrance of thy crucified God. Let thy God be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:23330:4"/>
J care not, he may then helpe thee. Thy annointed (the Priests) I will ſurely put to the plague. Wild beaſts &amp; wolues ſhall ſucke the breaſts of thy wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Thou ſhalt leaue and forſake thy Religion which thou hast. That which remaineth of all things ſhalbe conſumed with fire. Heerewith rest thou ſatisfied. I doe not tell thee now what I will doe, or meane to doe with thee, vnderſtand it if thou wilt or canſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From our reſidence <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> moſt ſtrongly garded.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:23330:5"/>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:23330:5"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO THE MENACING and VVarre-denouncing <hi>Letter of the Great</hi> Turke.</head>
            <byline>By <hi>SIGISMOND</hi> King of Polonia <hi>and Sweden: great Duke of Lituania,</hi> Ruſsia, and Podolia.</byline>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IGISMOND</hi> by the grace of God King of Polonia and Sweden, Great Duke of Litu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ania, Ruſsia, and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolia, one of the moſt humble ſeruants
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:23330:6"/>
of the great God, and of his ſonne Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt crucified.</signed>
               <salute>To AC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>METH chiefe Prince of Turkes and Infidels ſoules health.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>We haue receiued thy Letter fraught with threats, and ſwolen with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties againſt the Maieſtie of the high GOD, whereunto wee had not vouchſafed anſwere, but that wee were perſwaded, that our ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence would haue beene a meanes, to cauſe thee flatter thy ſelfe ſo much the more, elſe had we neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected thee like an arch-enemie of God as thou art. VVe haue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thought fit in ſome ſort, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the ſaluation of thy ſoule, letting thee know, that thou art no other but a meere man, in thy
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:23330:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
perſon more weake than many of thy followers, which ſhould cauſe thee to remember, that if it had not pleaſed God, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graue in the front of ſuch as rule a kind of awfull Maieſtie wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by their ſubiects are kept in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, the good by reward, the euill and peruerſe by rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous lawes, and both the one and the other by authoritie, it were impoſſible they ſhould continue eminent aboue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Thou then, who in thy ſelfe art but as other men, muſt know, that there is a ſupreame power of more might than thine, which doth vphold thine eſtate, cauſing thee to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:23330:7"/>
of thy followers. This power proceeds from God moſt good, moſt iuſt, moſt ſtrong, preſeruing it ſo long as Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces humble themſelues before him, but being once tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with preſumption &amp; pride, it eaſily abateth their furie. I will offer no other example to thy conſideration than that of Baiaſeth the Second, one of thy predeceſſours, who thinking to ſcale heauen with his armie, (which in the iudgement of man was vnreſiſtable, but in Gods ſight moſt contemptible) liued to ſee himſelfe vanquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, taken, and impriſoned, coopt vp in an iron cage (wherein
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:23330:7"/>
he was in triumph drawne after the victorious Conquerour) ſeruing him for no better than a footſtoole, &amp; hauing no other food than ſuch as was caſt him (like a dogge) from his Table<note n="*" place="margin">A iuſt guer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for his pride.</note>. Thinke then with thy ſelfe, that he that was ſo great, ſo puiſſant, and ſo fearefull may happily by right of ſucceſſion haue left vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee (as being deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded from him) the like, or a worſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, if thou doeſt dare to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue thy blaſphemies againſt God, and his beloued ſonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt crucified. Thou doeſt miſtake in thinking to lay an aſperſion vpon vs, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching vnto vs the Croſſe:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:23330:8"/>
for wee account it our chiefeſt honour and glorie; by vertue whereof as the Emperour <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantine</hi> quelled his enemies, we hope and aſſure our ſelues to be defended againſt thy fury. Thy proud and thundering words diſmay vs not, our courage is more maſculine and generous than ſo to bee outbraued: For know that wee regard not thy threats, but with all ſcorn tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vpon thy pride, and deride thy terrours. And in ſtead of thanking thee for aduertiſing vs before thy comming, wee bidde thee come when thou wilt: Thou ſhalt bee receiued contrary to thy expectation.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:23330:8"/>
Wee haue ſteepe mountaines and impregnable rockes, that ſhal barre thee from entring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our lands. Thou ſhalt finde our Cities and Caſtles wel fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with munition, our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non mouthes breathing furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fires, our courages inuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, our blades eager &amp; ſharpe, our armes impenetrable, our bodies apt to ſuſtaine the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of all ſeaſons, our mindes promiſing nothing but victory. And to dazell thine eies, the royall Standard of the bleſſed Croſſe ſhall goe before vs. But aboue all, the crucified Sonne of the great God ſhall cauſe his Angels to conduct vs and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:23330:9"/>
giue vs the victorie. Hee it is that ſhall be our Leader, vnder whoſe protection wee will not feare to braue thee at thy gates. Thy miſcreant troopes ſhall be trodden vnder foot, and their bellies trampled on, and by a happie victorie (if thou chance to ſcape our conquering arme) thou ſhalt find thy ſelfe purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto the moſt ſecret dennes of thy abominable Seraglio. Thou ſhalt ſee thy Moſquees laied leuel with the ground, thy Mophti and other the execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Prieſts of thy perfidious Mahomet made Galley-ſlaues, all thoſe traiterous runnagates whom thou doeſt harbor, ſhalt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:23330:9"/>
thou ſee put to exquiſite tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: of all which be moſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured. And then ſhall bee ſet free all thoſe poore and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Chriſtians, who now lie groaning vnder the burden of thy tyrannous yoke, whoſe wofull cries being mounted to heauen, haue iuſtly excited the vengeance of God vpon thee, who hath permitted thee to riſe to this height of pride, that thy ruine and deſtruction may bee the more exemplar vnto after ages. To conclude, thou ſhalt ſee the ſeruice of God reeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in Grecia and Aſia, which thou doeſt now vniuſtly vſurpe. But if it happen thee
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:23330:10"/>
to end thy miſerable life in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell (as wee hope that God will grant) be confident that all the aforeſaid vengeance ſhall enſue vpon thy death, and whileſt thy wretched ſoule ſhall lie broiling in the quenchleſſe flames of hel, we will lift vp our cheerfull voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and for the victorie obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ouer thee and thine, ſing praiſes vnto our God, to whom be glorie for euer.</p>
            <p>Know then, O Infidell, that we feare thee not at all: and if thou beeſt not bent to run head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto thine owne deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, be aduiſed. Content and containe thy ſelfe within thoſe bounds thou doeſt at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:23330:10"/>
vſurpe. And if thou haſt any beleefe at all, that thy thrice reuerenced Prophet Mahomet could tell a truth, or foretell fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture euents, then call to minde that of thoſe 1000. yeeres which he preſcribed for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thy Sect, there remaines not aboue 6. or 7. yeeres. This then is the time that the yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheathed ſwords of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans affoords for thy amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that thou maiſt come to the knowledge of the moſt true God, to worſhip him in his Son Ieſus Chriſt. VVhereunto we once more exhort thee, omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all other ſalutation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:23330:11"/>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at our Caſtle of Poſn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich, <date>the twelfth of Februarie, the yeere of the Incarnation of our Lord Ieſus 1613.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Sigiſmond.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:23330:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
